A Finding Aid to the William Page and Page Family Papers, 1815-1947, bulk 1843-1892, in the Archives of American Art AAA.pagewill
Archives of American Art
- Personal Business Records, 1848-1932, undated; Series 4; (Boxes 5 and 9; 0.2 linear feet)
  Records related to William Page's artwork include sales and shipping receipts; commission, consignment, and exhibition agreements; and inventories of artwork. Packenham and Hooker records consist of financial statements and loan agreements from the period when Page lived in Italy, including several notes specifying paintings as collateral for loans. Probate records document in detail the contestation of William Page's will by his daughters from his first marriage, Anne Rose and Emma Page Watson.
  Papers related to patents include a joint submission for a patent by Page and Francis G. Shaw for a boat steering mechanism and an improvement on a rifle ordnance by Page. Miscellaneous financial records consist mainly of bills and receipts for personal items, but also include receipts from Page's 1874 stay in Darmstadt, Germany, records of personal loans Page secured in Italy, a bank book, and tax receipts.
  Records from the National Academy of Design include drafts of memoranda of the Committee on Schools by multiple authors including Enoch Wood Perry, a manuscript fragment from a public address which is unsigned, a note to the N.A.D. Council from George Paterson, two unmarked ballots from 1871, and an exhibition announcement of 1885. Page Family records include financial records of the Page children and grandchildren, some of which relate to the estate of William Page.
  - William Page (Box 5)
    - Records Related to Artwork, 1859-1888, undated (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Packenham and Hooker (Maquay and Packenham) Accounts, 1850-1858, undated (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Draft of Last Will and Testament, 1877 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Probate of Last Will and Testament (Box 5)
      - Court Records, 1885-1890 (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Evidence, circa 1869-1887 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Patents, 1847, 1861, undated; (Oversized items housed in Box 9, sol) (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Miscellaneous Business Records, 1848-1892, undated (Box 5, Folder 44)
      (In addition to Page's records, file contains receipts for Sophia Page, Mrs. Henry Stevens, and Sarah Page, his second wife.)
  - National Academy of Design, 1870-1871, 1885, undated (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Page Family Records, 1880-1932, undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Stephen W. Hitchcock, Receipts and Estate Inventory, 1850-1852 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Charles F. Briggs Patent Report, 1861 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Oversized Patent Document (Items scanned with Box 5, folder 43) (Box 9 (sol))
- Printed Materials, 1845-1938, undated; Series 5; (Boxes 5-7, 9, OV 11; 1.6 linear feet)
  This series contains books, pamphlets, leaflets, clippings, catalogs, publicity, programs, calling cards, entire newspapers, and other printed materials. Works by William Page include a book on portraits of Shakespeare, a series of articles on Venetian painters published in The Independent in 1860, and other published lectures and articles. A scrapbook and loose clippings of columns by Sophia Page document a series of travel columns she wrote while living abroad in the 1850s, which were published in the New York Tribune.
  Also found are museum catalogs, gallery catalogs and newsletters, exhibition announcements, invitations, and tickets for exhibitions and collections containing artwork by William Page and others. Clippings about the Pages include reviews of Page's artwork, lectures, obituaries, and news items related to the probate trial and other subjects. Periodicals with articles related to William Page date from 1870 to 1885. Other periodicals, pamphlets, leaflets, books, and ephemera document a range of interests and activities of various members of the Page family.
  Not all of the printed material has been digitized, particularly exhibition catalogs of other artists, miscellaneous clippings, oversized newspapers, some collected periodicals, and miscellaneous ephemera.
  - Published Works by William Page (Box 5)
    - Newspapers with Articles and Lectures by Page, 1860, 1871, 1873, undated; (Oversized items housed in OV 11, not scanned) (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Shakespeare's Portraits, 1876; (partially scanned) (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Published Columns by Sophia Page, 1853-1857, undated; (2 folders; oversized items housed in OV 11, OV) (Box 5, Folder 51-52)
  - Artwork Catalogs and Announcements, 1855-1902, 1938, undated; (2 folders; partially scanned) (Box 5, Folder 53-54)
  - Exhibition Invitations and Tickets, 1856-1877 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Clippings (Box 5)
    - About William and Sophia Page, 1857-1902, undated; (Oversized items housed in Box 11, OV) (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Donation of Shakespeare Bust to Stratford-on-Avon, 1900 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Miscellaneous Clippings, 1845-1929, undated; (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 5, Folder 59-60)
    - Miscellaneous Clippings, 1845-1929, undated; (6 folders; not scanned) (Box 6, Folder 1-6)
  - Periodicals, 1870-1906; (7 folders; oversized items housed in Box 9, sol; partially scanned) (Box 6, Folder 7-13)
    (Page's 1879 article, "The Measure of a Man," has been torn from the magazine filed here. Page proofs of the article can be found in Notes and Writings)
  - Pamphlets and Leaflets, 1864-1931, undated; (4 folders; partially scanned) (Box 6, Folder 14-17)
  - Books (Box 6)
    - Books on Art Technique, 1849, undated; (Oversized items housed in Box 9, sol; partially scanned) (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Miscellaneous Books, 1839-1917, undated; (4 folders; partially scanned) (Box 6, Folder 19-22)
  - Ephemera (Box 6)
    - Programs for Cultural Events, 1876-1900, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Artists' Materials Advertisements, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Bookseller and Library Catalogs, 1858, 1870-1886, undated (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Miscellaneous Ephemera, 1849-1928, undated; (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 6, Folder 26-27)
  - Calling Cards and Business Cards, undated (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Halftone Prints and Postcards, undated (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Halftone Printing Block of William Page Portrait, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Printed Materials (Items scanned with Box 6, f7, 8, 10, 18) (Box 9 (sol))
  - Oversized Printed Materials (Items scanned with Box 5, f52, 57) (Box 11 (OV))
- Photographs, 1845-1947, undated; Series 6; (Box 7-9, OV 12, MGP 5-6; 1.4 linear feet)
  This series includes photographic portraits, snapshots, photographs of homes and other buildings, travel photographs, and photographs of works of art. Most portraits are mounted cabinet photographs or cartes-des-visites, but a small number of tintypes, daguerreotypes, and unmounted prints are also found. Portraits depict William Page, his family, descendants, and friends, as well as sitters for his painted portraits. Photographs after 1900 depict primarily the family of George S. Page, William Page's son, his wife and children, and their families.
  Several of the portraits from the 19th century were taken in the Brady studios of Matthew Brady, and a few from the Sarony studio in New York are also found. There is a large portrait of Page taken by Charles H. Williamson. Pencil tracings on several enlarged photographs, grid marks on cabinet photographs and tintypes, and color notes handwritten on photographs seem to indicate that some of these photographs were used as studies for paintings. Drawings of some of the photographic subjects are also found in the Artwork series.
  Most of the portraits and snapshots in this series are unidentified. Where subjects have been identified, their names appear in the folder list.
  Many of the photographs of works of art relate to Page's study of Shakespeare, including a collection of Shakespeare portraits and photographs of the supposed death mask of Shakespeare then in Darmstadt, Germany. Other photographs of works of art include a series of heliotypes of classical busts in the Gray Collection of Harvard College.
  Glass plate negatives are housed separately and closed to researchers.
  - Portrait Photographs (Box 7)
    - William Page, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Henry Ward Beecher, 1874, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Reuben E. Fenton, 1860-1875; (Oversized items housed in Box 9, sol) (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Emma A. Fortuna, 1882, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Sophia Stevens Page (daughter), 1882, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - William Page (grandson), 1889-1892, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Wendell Phillips, 1855-1865; (Oversized items housed in Box 9, sol) (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Winfield Scott, 1862 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - B.Frank and Charlotte Stevens, 1882 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Henry Stevens, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Simon Stevens, 1884, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Charles Sumner, 1856-1866, undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Unidentified, Multiple Views, undated; (3 folders; oversized items housed in Box 12, OV) (Box 7, Folder 14-16)
      (Image 4, identified after processing as Cornelius Vanderbilt)
    - Of Men, 1863-1890, undated; (2 folders, including copies; oversized items housed in Box 9, sol) (Box 7, Folder 17-18)
      (Includes portraits of James Russell Lowell, Charles W. Eliot, Admiral David Farragut, possibly Robert Browning, William Lloyd Garrison, Paul Christen__, Sanford Thayer, Edwin Liebfreed, and William R. O'Donovan)
    - Of Men, Unidentified, 19th century; (5 folders; oversized items housed in Box 12, OV; 1 glass plate negative housed in MGP 5) (Box 7, Folder 19-23)
    - Of Men, Unidentified, 20th century; (Not scanned) (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Of Women, 1882-1885, 1929, undated; (Oversized items housed in Box 9, sol) (Box 7, Folder 25)
      (Includes portraits of Emma Page Watson, Candace Page [both daughters of William Page], Bertie Maretzeh, Julia Butler, Alice B. Jepson, Mrs. George Stevens Page [daughter-in-law of William Page])
    - Of Women, Unidentified, 19th century; (6 folders; oversized items housed in Box 12, OV; 3 glass plate negatives housed in MGP 5 and MGP 6) (Box 7, Folder 26-31)
    - Of Women, Unidentified, 1922, undated; (Not scanned; oversized items housed in Box 9, sol) (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Of Couples and Groups, 1882, undated (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Of Children and Pets, 1882, undated; (2 folders; oversized items housed in Box 9, sol; 1 glass plate negative housed in MGP 5) (Box 7, Folder 34-35)
  - Snapshots, 1886-1887, undated (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Snapshots, 1906-1915, undated; (Not scanned) (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Snapshots, 1920-1947, undated; (Not scanned) (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Photographs of Places (Box 8 (hol))
    - Page Home in Tottenville, NY, 1904 (Box 8 (hol), Folder 1)
    - Lighthouse on Long Island Sound, 1872 (Box 8 (hol), Folder 2)
    - Tomb of Henry Stevens, Vermont, USA, undated (Box 8 (hol), Folder 3)
    - Travel Series from Great Britain and Switzerland, 19th century (Box 8 (hol), Folder 4)
    - Photographic Postcards of Bemus Point, NY, circa 1906; (Not scanned) (Box 8 (hol), Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous Places, 1865, undated; (Oversized items housed in Box 9, OV) (Box 8 (hol), Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Works of Art (Box 8 (hol))
    - Page's Bust and Portrait of Shakespeare, undated; (2 folders, including oversized glass negative; oversized items housed in OV 12 and artifact cabinet, drawer 1; not scanned) (Box 8 (hol), Folder 7-8)
    - Other Shakespeare Portraits, undated; (Not scanned) (Box 8 (hol), Folder 9)
    - Shakespeare Death Mask, circa 1870s; (Oversized items housed in Box 9, sol; not scanned) (Box 8 (hol), Folder 10)
    - "Farragut at Mobile" by Page, circa 1868; (Not scanned) (Box 8 (hol), Folder 11)
    - Heliotypes of Classical Busts, undated; (Oversized items housed in Box 12, OV; not scanned) (Box 8 (hol), Folder 12)
    - Works of Art by Others, 1880-1881, undated; (Oversized items housed in Box 9, sol; not scanned) (Box 8 (hol), Folder 13)
  - Oversized Photographs (Items scanned with Box 7 f4, 8, 17, 25, 32 and 34; Box 8 f6 and 10) (Box 9 (sol))
  - Oversized Photographs (Items scanned with Box 7 f14, 20 and 29; Box 8 f7, 12 and 13) (Box 12 (OV))
  - Glass Plate Negatives, 4 Glass negatives (Box MGP 5)
  - Glass Plate Negative, 1 Glass negatives (Box MGP 6)
- Artwork, 1856-1874, undated; Series 7; (Box 8, OV 13-16, rolled documents 17-19; 0.6 linear feet and 3 rolled documents)
  This series includes sketches and drawings in pencil, graphite, and pastel; oil paintings; and fine prints. Subjects are mostly portraits, although some classical subjects and a landscape drawing are also found. Most of the artwork is unsigned. A few of the drawings bear Page's handwriting and one is dated 1856. One drawing is signed C. Page and may be the work of Page's daughter Candace, who attended art school in the 1890s.
  Sketches and drawings include finished drawings, rough sketches, and line drawings on tracing paper. Among the line drawings are copies of Titian and Page paintings and figure drawings which were published with Page's essay on proportion, "The Measure of Man." A number of the more finished drawings resemble photographic portraits in the Photographs series. Named subjects include Charlotte Cushman, Catherine Hayes, and the son of M.I. Bard. Other subjects recognizable from Page's photographs and paintings include Reuben Fenton, W.R. O'Donovan, a self-portrait of Page, and Titian.
  Prints include an engraving of Page's painting "Farragut at Mobile," an untitled portrait by Page, and a lithograph showing a Shakespeare bust. Other prints include a print made and signed by A.B. Durand, prints of classical paintings by Rubens and Titian, and of paintings by Page's contemporaries. A large collection of Italian prints of anatomical drawings are also found.
  A few of the drawings depict subjects in 20th century clothing and could not be William Page's work. Because so few of the works of art in this small series are identified by artist or by date, all items have been sorted by media and interfiled. Not all of the artwork has been digitized.
  - Sketches and Drawings, 1856, undated; (2 folders; oversized items housed in OV 13, 14, and 15 and rolled documents; partially scanned) (Box 8 (hol), Folder 14-15)
  - Paintings, undated; (Oversized items housed in OV 14 and 15) (Box 8 (hol), Folder 16)
  - Prints of William Page Artwork, undated; (Oversized items housed in OV 16) (Box 8 (hol), Folder 17)
  - Signed Print by A.B. Durand, 1872; (Oversized items housed in Box 9, sol) (Box 8 (hol), Folder 18)
  - Prints of Other Artists' Work, undated; (Oversized items housed in OV 16 and 17; not scanned) (Box 8 (hol), Folder 19)
  - Prints of Anatomical Drawings, undated; (Oversized items housed in OV 16 and 17; not scanned) (Box 8 (hol), Folder 20)
  - Notes Taken from Portrait Subject and Shakespeare Death Mask, circa 1874, undated; (Oversized items housed in Box 9, sol) (Box 8 (hol), Folder 21)
  - Oversized Signed Print by A.B. Durand (Items scanned with Box 8, f18) (Box 9 (sol))
  - Oversized Notes on Artwork (Items scanned with Box 8, f21) (Box 9 (sol))
  - Oversized Sketches and Drawings (Items scanned with Box 8, f15) (Box 13 (OV))
  - Oversized Sketches and Drawings (Items scanned with Box 8, f15) (Box 14 (OV))
  - Oversized Paintings (Items scanned with Box 8, f16) (Box 14 (OV))
  - Oversized Drawings (Box 15 (OV))
  - Oversized Paintings (Box 15 (OV))
  - Oversized Prints (Items scanned with Box 8, f17, 19 and 20) (Box 16 (OV))
  - Oversized Prints (Items scanned with Box 8, f19 and 20) (Box 17 (OV))
  - Oversized Shakespeare Drawing (See Box 8, f15) (Box 18 (RD))
  - Oversized Shakespeare Drawing (See Box 8, f15) (Box 19 (RD))
  - Oversized 20th Century Drawings (See Box 8, f15) (Box 20 (RD))